I stumbled across this video where Dr
Peter Atia a well-known physician had
several interesting things to say about
saunas and our health I'd like to hear
what he has to say in an interview and
then I'd like to sprinkle in some
additional information especially
cracking open some of the studies to see
if there's truth to the claims here
here's Dr AA on why he changed his mind
about sauna use something else I've
changed my mind on yeah I'm way way way
more bullish on sauna than I
before I used to be in the camp of SAA
feels great it maybe even helps you
sleep a bit better um that's probably
about it like there's no way you're
going to really live longer because
you're in a sauna and while truthfully
we don't have really great prospective
data um or sorry I should say we have
good prospective data we don't have good
randomized data real quick here in
Translation Dr AA is talking about
prospective data meaning we have good
ass asstive studies that are pre-planned
and follow people's habits over time but
we don't have good randomized data
meaning intervention studies these are
the type of studies that give us
definitive ideas on causation because
we're controlling for all other
variables and simply changing one thing
called an intervention you can imagine
it's extremely difficult if not almost
impossible to put people into one group
getting sauna treatment and then and uh
the comparison group gets nothing
obviously it introduces a potential for
what's known as the placebo effect where
participants think something will affect
them so they are more prone to
experience an effect not because the
intervention causes a true effect but
simply because the belief itself there
are many many instances of that
happening in science and that's why
having a proper control especially a
placebo group is critical for reducing
that risk that all said I actually
slightly ever so slightly disagree with
Dr AA here because there are some decent
randomized control trials on sauna use
like these as a start usually I'm the
conservative one when it comes to
interventions but there have been
randomized control trials on sauna
dating back over two decades now they
still largely suffer from the whole you
know Placebo issue that I mentioned but
they are randomized and controlled to
the best possible anyway I wanted to
explain the distinction here I think
this is one of those things where the
burden of evidence in the non-randomized
data is so
strong it's becoming hard to ignore so
most of the research in this subject has
come out of Finland and the son surprise
yeah
um and so there's the obvious issues
with this right right the people who can
afford danuna are by definition going to
have more time on their hands more
disposable income probably more
education like all of the standard uh
things on top of that if you're going to
choose to sauna because you believe it's
healthy what else are you doing because
you believe it is healthy I mean right
so so you know if if the data showed
that Sauna versus non sauna was like a
5% Improvement in mortality it would be
hard to get that excited about it but
when you look at the largest published
series on this you see a benefit in all
cause mortality a relative absolute
pardon me a relative risk reduction of
40% and an absolute risk reduction of
like
18% those are those are high numbers
those are ridiculous numbers okay so
he's getting into the long-term data the
prospective data that he mentioned
earlier so are the effects that big and
can we possibly contr control for some
of the Hidden factors that he mentioned
we can lean on this finished study which
I'll likely cover more in the future but
I'd like to touch on it in relation to
all cause mortality as Dr AA mentioned
similar work in this study researchers
recruited over 2,000 participants and
followed them and their habits over 20
years and then Quantified sauna use or
no SAA use and the relationship to death
otherwise called all cause of mortality
well what did they find
well in this table they quantify the all
cause mortality risk in these people
based on the amount of sauna the top the
reference there the one is the people
who sauna once per week or less the two
sections underneath are all cause
mortality risk relative to the
reference when doing sauna more than
once per week the risk is reduced by 30
to 40% confirming Dr aa's point but the
data that we went over is largely
unadjusted meaning it's a pretty pure
correlation except that the researchers
is controlled for age on the other hand
the researchers did perform more robust
adjustments for things like weight blood
pressure blood cholesterol containing
lipoprotein smoking alcohol consumption
previous heart disease type 2 diabetes
overall cardiorespiratory Fitness
resting heart rate physical activity and
socioeconomic status after adjusting for
all those factors
the all cause mortality risk reduction
was still
maintained now to be clear this still
doesn't eliminate the possibility for
confounding variables as in something
else explaining these results since as
Dr AA pointed out people who sauna more
often may simply be more aware of the
potential benefits so they may have a
more Leisure Time uh they may have more
time to go to the gym uh they may have
healthier habits and so on however what
I love that the researchers did here is
use multiple adjustments for some major
confounding factors for example if a
person is generally healthier then that
would reflect in their cardiorespiratory
Fitness as well as their blood pressure
as well as their heart rate and physical
activity they'd be accounted for by one
but likely many of those controls then
Leisure Time and overall wealth would be
accounted for in socioeconomic status or
at least a high likelihood and even if a
few fall between the cracks it's
unlikely that they'd actually sway the
analysis all that to say that Dr AA is
spoton oh and by the way there's
something a bit comical but important
that contributed to possibly increased
sudden cardiac death in people doing
sauna I'll discuss that at the end I'd
like to touch on some other aspects
first but first I've been analyzing a
lot of studies on sauna therapy across a
number of different protocols and I've
compiled all the protocols across a
multitude of studies from infrared to
steam and so on including the common
themes of what's shown to be most
effective it's available for the
physionic Insiders and is continuously
updated as new therapies are released if
you're interested the Insiders includes
those protocols but also many other
protocols a massive library of
application folus videos monthly podcast
and much more it's linked in the
description box if you're so inclined
hope to see you there anyway there's
more to be said about sauna so let's get
to it if you think about what the
mechanism of action is yeah I was going
to ask you next is it heat chock
proteins is it something else I think
it's many things I think it's heat chock
proteins I think it's nitric oxide I
think it's like literally vascular tone
right reduction in blood pressure in
Spitfire mode a few of the mentioned
mechanisms heat shock proteins and Nitro
oxide from sauna use well for one heat
chock proteins which are well proteins
inside the cell that attach to
functional proteins within the cell and
stabilize them essentially if the cell
undergo stress components of the cell
can be damaged and heat shock proteins
can bind to various molecules in the
cell and stabilize them disallowing them
from unfolding and becoming inert if
this lasts long term it might protect
against other stressors that our cells
experience anyway there have been
studies that have looked at heat shock
proteins in sauna use and identified as
seen here that a single bout of sauna
can increase she heat shock proteins in
the body both conditions orange and
green were exposed to sauna so there's
no control condition as we can see the
after the first sauna here there's an
increase in HSP abbreviation for heat
shock protein however h should be noted
that heat shock proteins normalize or
reduce long term because after 10 sauna
sessions heat shock proteins have
reduced but importantly they are still
increased relative to Baseline I'd like
to look at more data on the topic but it
seems to be true that sauna does induce
heat shock proteins although I'm not
entirely convinced it occurs long term
at least not based on these data but
what about nitric oxide well briefly
nitric oxide is a molecule that when
released from the endothelial cells
inside your blood vessels your arteries
can bind smooth muscle cells also found
in your arteries and Signal them to
relax this relaxation is called a
vasodilation and allows blood pressure
to be reduced because there is more room
for the same blood volume to move
through so to assess the role sauna has
on nitric oxide we can lean on this
study and we look at the nitric oxide
levels and we can see the vertical axis
is the amount of nitric oxide so both
lines indicate groups where Sona was
applied there is again no control group
this is a confusing way to show the data
so I'll just point your attention to
focus on the far right so two c and the
far left one one indicates no Sonic
exposure so Baseline 2 C indicates a
full day after the 10th sauna
session evidently there is a long-term
effect of increasing nitric oxide which
is encouraging I would actually like to
see error bars or standard deviations
but if we suspend our need for exactness
which is difficult for me to do at times
if I'm honest but uh these data indicate
Dr AA is again on the mark also Dr AA
mentions this um it's an SL you know
increase in heart rate and cardiac
output so there's a bit of an exercise
benefit um I don't know if bdnf I think
bdnf has been measured I can't recall
that could be another uh potential
benefit so my guess is brain derve
neurot Factor yeah I think it's probably
half a dozen things that are all moving
in the right direction so Dr AA mentions
sauna is like exercise mimetic and
that's likely true but as he also
mentions it might not be exclusively
that and that is likely also true oh and
on the bdnf front he remembers correctly
bdnf a molecule that's been identified
as being highly beneficial for our brain
is also elevated according to this study
okay so we covered a ton of information
so what are the key takeaways oh and
that thing I teased earlier about the uh
increased Health complications from
sauna in this study the researchers
mentioned there were some more serious
complications like sudden cardiac death
if people consumed alcohol while
saing so obviously death is tragic but
I'm not sure why people felt inclined to
get to drinking seems unwise when you're
already sweating heavily anyway that's
the caution although I think you already
realize that's obvious don't drink in
sauna and wear seat belt while you're at
it in your in your car okay the
takeaways it's pretty simple Dr AA is
correct and if you can manage it using a
sauna more than once per week seems to
provide some outsized health benefits
that ultimately yield a reduction in all
cause mortality of up to 40% reduced
risk which is a huge relative effect and
if you're so inclined to learn more like
the effect on your heart I'd recommend
this linked video it goes far more into
depth thanks for tuning in
[Music]